Well, the next question is a bit
tough.
But what do you hate about YouTube?
Hi guys!
What a special video we have today.
As you've probably seen in the thumbnail,
today we have a collaboration with María and
Cody from Learn Spanish with Why Not Spanish.
And although they really don't need an introduction
because I'm sure you know them, I
'm going to tell you a little bit about them.
Well, Maria is a Colombian Spanish teacher
.
Cody, who is American, speaks Spanish
as a second language.
And although he also appears in the videos
on many occasions, he is more in charge of
the technical side.
So they make a perfect pair and complement each other
to create those great Spanish learning videos
you see on their channel.  They
both now live in Bogotá and, in addition to
teaching Spanish, they occasionally go out
and show real-life situations,
such as: the supermarket, the shoe store,
etc.
Whether you know them or not, I'll leave you
the link in the description and also the
video we made for their channel,
so you can see the two parts we made.
Well, here we are with my namesake María
from the Why Not Spanish channel, and we're going to
chat with her a little.
Hello Maria!
How are you?
- Maria from Why Not Spanish: Hello Maria!
Super good, and how are you?
- Maria Español: Welcome!
Thank you so much for being here, I'm really
excited. We're going to be chatting, you know,
to get to know you a little better.
What do you think? Are you ready?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Very good!
Thank you so much for inviting me. I've
seen your videos too, and I'm so happy to
finally be chatting with you now.
- María Español: The truth is yes, it
's a pleasure for me that you're here, really.
Oh, I have to tell the viewers that they
have to go check out another video we just
recorded for Maria and Cody's channel.
So I'm also going to leave the link
in the description so you can go check it out.
And, let's start talking about the beginning,
let's start at the beginning.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Ready.
- María Español: About how you started
this channel, what was the hardest part for you.
- María from Why Not Spanish: María, what was
hardest for us, the hardest thing for us
at the beginning, was getting more than 5 people to
watch our videos.
At first, only our moms and our
friends watched the videos, and no one else.
So, for us it was a struggle.  It
was very difficult to get more people
than just our inner circle to watch our
videos.
Now, what's hardest for us is perhaps making
the simplest videos, because we're very
detail-oriented and focus on things that
other people might not notice.
- María Español: I understand you.
But really, I think it's normal, right?
Start and only have a few people see you.
I think it has happened to all of us.
I confess to you: "My mother hasn't seen my channel
yet."  I
don't show it to him.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Really?
And why do you do that?
- María Español: Because I'm embarrassed.
I am very shy.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Oh, don't tell me.
- María Español: I'm not going to ask you about
that either, but no, no.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Okay.
- María Español: My friends and family
don't usually watch my channel.  So no.
That wasn't my beginning, no.
Well, they told me that people should watch
the video, but you had difficulties with some aspects,
for example, preparing videos, writing scripts, coming
up with ideas, editing.
What was the most difficult thing?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well, maybe
not editing, because well, the person who
has been in charge of 90% of the
video editing is Cody.
And he already had experience, because he studied
to do this.
So, he edits, he does everything related
to technology.
But in my case, I had never been in front
of a camera.
And perhaps for me the hardest thing was that,
getting used to speaking in front of a camera
and letting go because it was a lot for me...well,
still.
But before it was much more, they made me nervous,
I got very nervous, more nervous than
now.  I did
n't like it, I felt very uncomfortable with
that feeling.
Maybe that was the hardest thing for me.
- María Español: She can understand you perfectly,
too.  I
identify myself.
Well, the next question is a bit
tough.
But what do you hate about YouTube?
I mean, everything, I'm not just talking about the
platforms, I'm talking about the whole process.
What do you hate, if anything,
or what do you hate about YouTube?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Let's see, well.
From the creation process, I hate, I hate making
subtitles.
I find it tedious, very boring.
But hey, I understand that
they help many people.  I
used to do subtitles in English and Spanish,
but looking at statistics and things,
I realized that people on my channel
don't watch or use English subtitles.
So I stopped making them, Maria.  I
already said "no more".
and now I only do the subtitles in
Spanish, nothing else.
- María Español: Well, nothing more.
It's a lot.
I used to do them manually, and it was the
worst.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Yes, it's horrible.
- María Español: I confess that I don't
make them now.
I do everything, but subtitles are the only thing
my mental health doesn't allow me to do, because it
's, as you say, tedious, it's impossible.
Well, if we think about what happens when
the camera's off, what happens when you go
do what you love to do, what
motivates you, what do you enjoy most
in your free time?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Yes, I like
that question.
Well, I'm just learning to skate now,
recently.
Well, let's just say that almost a year ago I started
learning to skate and it's been something that
has changed my life, Maria.
I really enjoyed learning...
- María Español: Really?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Yes, learning
to skate, everything, the falls, the obstacles,
the fear that you have to overcome, because I had never
put on skates in my life.
So that's been something really interesting
- María Español: Never?!
Not even as a child?
- María from Why Not Spanish: No, not even
as a child, well maybe as a child
I used them once, but it wasn't anything serious and I didn't
do it very frequently.
So now I'm learning to skate
and it's been the best discovery of my 30s.
So, I love doing that, I've taken lessons,
I've fallen a few times, but I really enjoy it
.
So, in my free time I really enjoy
skating, and when I'm not skating I
really enjoy taking care of my plants.
In the house I have approximately 15 plants,
more or less.
Here in Colombia we say "matas", I have 15
or so plants if I'm not mistaken.
- María Español: Really?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Yes.
And then I spend a lot of time taking care of them,
watering them, checking that they don't have pests
or that the leaves aren't wilted.
That entertains me and relaxes me a lot.
- María Español: How good!
Which is the longest-lived of your plants?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well,
I have some plants that I inherited from my mom
and others that I got
myself.
So perhaps the longest-lived, the one that has been there the
longest is a small, miniature orange tree
that I have on the balcony, up above.
- María Español: And how long,
how long are we talking about?
Maria from Why Not Spanish: Well, I think
she's about 7 years old, 8 years old or so.
- María Español: I've never had a plant
that lasts this long.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well, that
plant is an inheritance from my mother.
So let's say I took over taking care of her,
but my mom did the hardest work
.
- María Español: Ah, well, don't
take any credit away from yourself.  It
is also a merit to take care of her for so long.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Okay, fine.
- María Español: Oh yeah, I was going to tell you
that I've seen you skating, because you sometimes upload
a video to Instagram and I've seen you
skating.
Very good evolution.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Pretty slow,
pretty slow, but we're slowly making progress.
The important thing is to continue doing what you
want, little by little, without rushing, but without pausing.
- María Español: Hey, doesn't it happen to you? Now
that you're talking about skating, doesn't it happen to you that
every thing you learn or every activity
you do makes you think a little about teaching
Spanish, learning Spanish?
Because it's a little bit...it's not the same,
but the mental process is the same,
right?
You get frustrated, you have to keep going, and try again the next day
, right?  Is
n't that a little...?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well, totally.  They
are not the same skills, but
the learning process
and the evolution process are closely related.
For example, I was embarrassed to go out
on skates, I was afraid.
But then these are processes that are
closely related to language learning and
everything that has to do with going out and speaking,
using Spanish, and all that.
- María Español: Yes.
Doing something that scares you, that's a challenge,
and that makes you feel good at the same time.  It's
both.
- María from Why Not Spanish:
- María Español: Yes, doing something that
scares you, that is a challenge and that at the same time
makes you feel good.  It's
both.
Well, let's continue.
Okay, the next question is related,
because this was "what things amuse you?",
but also what things make you happy?  What are the
things like that in everyday life,
little things or whatever you think makes you
happy, that make you happy?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well,
actually, María, very simple things make me happy
, very simple things.
For example, a sunny morning, the sun
rises and the sky is blue, beautiful.
That makes me very happy. It also makes me very happy to
see my dog Maya playing, running, having fun,
that makes me happy.
And also, as far as I can think now,
it's a good meal, well prepared, with lots of
flavor.
I love to eat, and eat well.
So, a good meal makes me feel
very happy.
- María Español: And do you prefer to cook or do you
prefer someone to cook for you?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well, that's a good
question.
Depends.
If I have someone in the house, or if I have
guests, I prefer to cook.
I like to cook for other people.
But if I'm alone, I get very bored.
I don't like the idea of cooking for myself.
- María Español: I understand you, the same thing happens to me
.
If I'm alone, I do something quick;
If there's anyone else...
- Maria from Why Not Spanish: Yes...
Yesterday we made a sandwich.
- María Español: What is that?  I
love it.
A sandwich.
- Maria from Why Not Spanish: Well, I think
you say "sandwich."
- Maria Español: Oh!
a sandwich.
Here we say "a sandwich."
- María from Why Not Spanish: Ok, a snack.
- María Español: And what did you say?
What was the word?
- María from Why Not Spanish: How curious,
because...
We say "un sánduche"
- María Español: I love the word.  I
love it.
I mean, it's like the adapted form of the
English word, right?
- María from Why Not Spanish: That's right.
And it's very curious because for us a "bocadillo"
is a guava sweet.
- María Español: Look, another day we have to
make a whole video just about these
vocabulary differences and everything, because it's fascinating.  I
had never heard the word.
Here we do use the word "sandwich"
too, but if we do, "sandwich"
is with sliced bread;  And if we say "sandwich"
it is with the typical oven-baked bread.  I
don't know how to differentiate it, but it's typical
bakery bread.
That would be the difference between the two words
for us.
But I'd never heard of "sandwich."
I like it.
- María from Why Not Spanish: So you
don't say "sandwich"?
- Maria Español: No, no.
To me, "sandwich" sounds Mexican, right?
- María from Why Not Spanish: A, then it must
be the Mexicans.
Tell me, tell us in the comments
if you know who says that.
Because I thought it was the Spanish,
but no.
- María Español: That's it.
Yes, yes, let them tell us.
I'm sure they know, because they know tons
of varieties.
With the one from Spain, I can't know more.
But anyway, I'll give you another question.
I have another question for you, because I asked you
"what makes you very happy?"
And I also want to ask you about where you
live, your country, your city.
So, I want to know: What do
you like most about your city, or your country in general?
Whatever you want.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well, that
's very easy.
From my city, Bogotá (I am from Bogotá,
I live in Bogotá).
I love the gastronomic offerings in Bogotá
.  There
are many restaurants here of all kinds,
of all flavors, from all countries.
You never get bored of trying
new restaurants.
There are many restaurants and, in addition, there is a wide
variety of cultural offerings.
There are free activities, and also paid ones.
For me, Bogotá is a very fun city.  It's
not an easy city, it's not a city
for everyone.
It's a big, busy, hectic,
slightly chaotic city.
But it's a very fun city.
I love living in Bogotá.
- María Español: The people of Bogotá, what do
you love about the people of Bogotá?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well,
that's very curious.
Because all Colombians come here to Bogotá.
Here in Bogotá you find a little Colombia.
People from the coasts, the
plains, and different regions of the country come here
to live and work.
So you find a lot of diversity.
I say that a Bogota native isn't really
someone who was born and raised here in Bogotá,
but rather someone who lives in Bogotá, because you
find people from all over the country.
A lot of variety.
Well, what I like most about Colombia is
that, thanks to its geography, we can enjoy
different climates.
So, for example, you live here in Bogotá
(which is a rather cold city) and you got bored
of the cold, so you just get
in your car and drive 3 hours, and you end up in
a city with a warmer climate.
So, I love that.
- María Español: Totally different, right?  It
may seem like you've gone to another country without
actually leaving.  It
seems like you have traveled to another place.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Absolutely, yes.
So, I like that: that diversity that
you find because of the geography, thanks to the
geography of the country.
- María Español: Now I'm looking forward to going
to Colombia, after what you're telling me.
- María from Why Not Spanish: You are welcome here.
You have a place to stay here and everything.
- María Español: Hey, that's great.
Hey, I'll take you at your word.
Careful. Okay, let's get to the last
questions.  I'm
going to ask you a very short one, so you can
tell me what you like most about Cody.
Because, of course, we're talking here, you
and I, but he's a very important piece
of "why not Spanish."
So, let's talk a little bit
about him too.
What do you like most about Cody?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Absolutely, you're
right.
I've always said that if it weren't for him,
I wouldn't be making YouTube videos.
First of all, he was the person who
convinced me to make videos and appear
on screen like that.
He was the person with the idea to do this.
And, in addition, he's the person in charge of
the videos, the technology: all that
stuff that I don't like.  It
is very important.
- María Español: You are very lucky.
- María from Why Not Spanish: The truth is yes.
Well, if I were alone maybe I would pay
to do it, but it wouldn't be the same.  It
wouldn't be the same.
I think maybe I wouldn't even do it.
So, well, what I like most about Cody
is his determination.
When Cody sets his mind to something he wants to do,
he puts all his effort into achieving it, and he does it.
And on top of that, he's a
problem solver, he doesn't give up. When other people would
say, "Oh no, this problem is too
complicated, I can't do it, let's
stop here," Cody says, "No, let's solve it."
And I don't know how he does it, but he finds the
solution.
So that's what I like and admire most
about Cody.
- María Español: How beautiful! How beautiful.
Well, here's a…
a statement.
Beautiful.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Almost, almost.
- María Español: Well, I think that since
we're running out of time, we'll leave it
here for today.
But, well, I really want to
ask you more questions, to be honest.
Because I think both me and everyone else
love to know a little more about the person.
That is, we see the teacher, but we also
really like getting to know the person.
So maybe we could get together
another time.
What do you think?
- María from Why Not Spanish: Well, I would love to,
María.
I love chatting with you.
You have a very special energy.
So, I'm delighted.
- María Español: That's great.
Well, nothing more, then.  We'll
leave it until next time.
Thank you so much, Maria, for being
here.
thanks also to Cody.
Thanks also to Maya, who I know is
there supporting me from wherever she is. I don't see her,
but she's definitely around.
- María from Why Not Spanish: From her bed.  He
is supporting us from his bed.
He's here sleeping.
- María Español: Well, it's the best place,
really. If we could also be
in bed, it would be fantastic.
But here we are more visible.
Well, nothing, see you next time and a
big hug.
And to the spectators, well, nothing more.
You have to go to María and Cody's channel
right now to watch the video we made on
their channel.
And we'll see you very soon.
Chao.
- María from Why Not Spanish: Thank you very much.
[End of interview]
And that's all, that's all for today.
I hope you enjoyed listening to this
real conversation, and that you also
enjoyed getting to know Maria a little better.
I loved having her on the channel,
I hope we get together again soon.
So, let me know
what you think in the comments, and I'll be reading
and answering as much as I can.
A kiss and see you next time.